in this video and show you a slightly
在这个视频中 我将给出一个
more complex example where the slope of
更加复杂的例子 在这个例子中
the function can be different at different points in the function
函数在不同点处的斜率是不一样的
let's start with an example here I plot to the
先来举个例子 我在这里画一个函数
function f of a equals a squared let's
f(a)等于a的平方
take a look at the point in equals two
来看看a等于2的点
so a squared or F of a is equal to four
在这个点上 a的平方等于4
let's nudge a slightly to the right so
让我们稍稍往右推进一点点
now a is equal to two point zero zero
现在a等于2.001
one f of a which is a squared is going
而f(a) 即a的平方
to be approximately four point zero zero
大约为4.004
four it turns out that the exact value
但是 如果你用计算器算的话
if you call the calculator and figure this out is actually four point zero
这个准确的值应该为
zero four zero zero one now I'm just to
4.004001 我只是为了简便起见
say a 4.04 is close enough so what this
省略了后面的部分
means is that when a is equal to two
所以这里想表达的是 当a等于2时
let's plot that here so if this is a is
我们把它画在这里
equal to 2 F of a is equal to four but
如果a等于2的话 那么f(a)就等于4
when I nudge a little bit to the right
但是当我稍稍往右移动一点的时候
two point zero zero one then it goes up to the x
即a=2.001的时候 注意这里
and y-axes are not to scale here then it
图上的x轴和y轴是不成比例的
goes up to about four point zero zero
然后这里的y大约为4.004
four again the x and y-axes here are not
再次注意这里的x轴和y轴是不成比例的
drawn to scale let's draw this on the
我们重新在图上画一下
plot so what we're saying is that if a
如果a等于2的话
is equal to 2 then F of a is equal to 4
那么f(a)就等于4
and here at the x and y axes are not
注意这里x轴和y轴的比例还是不太准确
drawn to scale technically this vertical
实际上这个点的高度
height should be much higher than this
要比这里纵轴的x值
horizontal height so the x and y axes
还要大那么一点点 所以x轴和y轴
are not on the same scale um but if I
还是不成比例的
now nudge a to 2.001 then F of a
如果让a等于2.001
becomes roughly 4.004 so if you draw this
则f(a)约为4.004 如果你在这儿画
little triangle again what this means is
一个小三角形 你就会发现
that if I nudge a to the right by 0.001 f
如果把a往右移动0.001
of a goes up four times as much by 0.004
那么f(a)将增大四倍 即增大0.004
so in the language of calculus we say
在微积分中 我们把这个
that the slope that is the derivative
此三角形斜边的斜率
from F of a at a equals 2 is 4 or to
称为f(a)在点a=2处的导数(即为4)
write this out with calculus notation
或者写成微积分的形式
we say that d/da of f of a is equal to 4
当a等于2的时候
when a is equal to 2 now one thing about
d/da f(a)等于4 由此可知
this function f of a equals a square is
函数f(a)=a^2
that the slope is different for
在a取不同值的时候
different values of a this is different
它的斜率是不同的 这和
and the example we saw on the previous slide
上个视频中的例子是不同的
so let's look at a different point if a
现在换个点来看看
is equal to 5 so except equals 2 now you
如果a等于5(不再等于2)
have a equals 5 then a squared is equal to 25
a等于5 那么a的平方则为25
so that's f of a if I nudge a to the
所以这是f(a)的值 如果再一次
right again
把a往右移一点点
it's tiny little nudge of a so now a is 5
只是移动非常小的一段距离
point 0 0 1 then F of a will be
现在a等于5.001 而f(a)的值
approximately 25 point 0 1 0 so what we
大约为25.010 由此可见
see is that by nudging a up by 0.001 F
当我们只往右移动了0.001时
of a goes up 10 times as much so we have
f(a)却增大了10倍
that d da f of a is equal to 10 when a
即可以写作d/da f(a)等于10
is equal to 5 because F of a goes up 10
而此时a的值为5 这里只是小小地
times as much as a does when I make a
移动了a 就使得f(a)的值
tiny little nudge to a so one way to see
增大了10倍 这里有种直观的方法可以解释
why the derivative is different at
为什么一个点的斜率
different points is that if you draw
在不同位置会不同 如果你在曲线上
that here a little triangle right at different locations on this you see that
的不同位置画一些小小的三角形 你就会发现
the ratio of the height of the triangle
三角形高和宽的比值
over the width of the triangle is very
在曲线上不同的地方
different at different points on the
它们是不同的
curve so here the slope is equal to 4
所以当a=2时，这里
when a is equal to 2 but is equal to 10
的斜率为4 而当a=5时
when a is equal to 5 now if you pull up
这里的斜率为10 如果你翻看
a calculus textbook a calculus textbook will tell you that
微积分的课本 课本会告诉你
d/da of f of a so f of a is equal to a
d/da f(a) 这里f(a)等于a的平方
square so that d/da of a squared one of the
所以d/da f(a)的值
formulas you find that the calculus
由课本上的公式可知
textbook is that this thing the slope of
这个函数f(a)=a^2的斜率
the function a squared is equal to 2a
应该等于2a
I'm not going to prove this but the way you
我不会在这里证明这个公式
find yours out is that you open up a
但是你可以打开你的微积分课本
calculus textbooks to the table formulas
找到上面的公式表
and it'll tell you the derivative of two
它会告诉你f(a)=a^2
of a squared is equal to 2a and indeed
的导数确实为2a
this is consistent with what we've
事实上这也和我们
worked out mainly when a is equal to 2
手工算的结果一样 当a为2时
the slopes of function to a is 2 times 2
函数的斜率为2乘以2
is therefore equal to 4 and when a is
即等于4 当a为5时
equal to 5 then the slope of the
函数的斜率为
function 2 times a is 2 times 5 is equal
2乘以a 即2乘以5等于10
to 10 so if you ever pull up a calculus
如果你翻看微积分课本
textbook and you see this formula that
你会看到这个公式
the derivative of a squared is equal to
即a的平方的导数等于2a
2a all that means is that for any given
这意味着任意给定一点a
value of a if you nudge it up with by
如果你稍微将a
0.001 already your tiny little value you
增大0.001
would expect f of a to go up by 2a that
那么你会看到f(a)将增大2a
is the slope or the derivative times
即增大的值为点在a处斜率或导数
however much you had an urge to the
乘以你向右移动的距离
right the value of a now one tiny little
现在 有个小细节需要注意
detail you know I have used these
之前我在这里
approximate symbols here and this wasn't
使用了一些不精确的值 这里的值
exactly 4.04 there's an extra point 001
不应该为4.04 你知道这里
you know there it turns out that this
应该还有额外001 这里有
extra pont 001 this little thing here is
额外的001 是因为
because we were nudging a to the right
我们把a向右移动了0.001
by 0.001 if we're instead nudging it to
然而 如果我们把a
the right by this new infinitesimally
向右移动像这样一个非常非常小的值
small value then this extra ever term
那么这个额外的项
will go away and you find that the
将可以被忽略 这样的话
amount that f of a goes up is exactly
你会发现f(a)增大的值
equal to the derivative times the amount
刚好等于导数乘以
that you nudged to the right and
你向右边移动的距离
the reason why is not 4.004 exactly is
至于为什么不是刚好等于4.004
because derivatives are defined using
是因为导数就是根据
this infinitesimally small not just to
这个极小值来定义的
a rather than you know 0.001 which is
而这里的0.001虽然比较小
well and while 0.001 is small is not
但是它还不足以小到
infinitesimally small so that's why the
可以被忽略 这就是为什么
amount that effort where it went up
例子中导数增大的值
isn't exactly given by the formula but
不是刚好等于导数公式算出来的值
is only kind of approximately given by
而只是根据导数算出来的一个估计值
the derivative to wrap up this video
为了总结这堂课所学的知识
let's just go through a few more quick
我们再来看看几个例子
examples the example you've already seen
之前你已经知道的是
is that if f of a equals a squared then
f(a)等于a的平方
in calculus textbooks formula table will
按照微积分课本上的写法
tell you that the derivative is equal to
这个函数的导数应该为2a
2a and so the example we went through
和之前的例子一样
was that if a is equal to 2 f of a
如果a等于2 那么f(a)等于4
equals 4 and if we nudge a so it's a
如果我们把a向右边移动一点
little bit bigger then f of a is about
那么f(a)将增大一点 大约为4.004
4.004 and so f of a went up four times as
所以f(a)增大了向右移动距离的四倍
much and indeed when a is equal to 2 the
所以事实上 当a等于2时
derivative is equal to 4 let's look at
导数的值为4
some other examples let's say instead
来看看其他例子
f of a is equal to a cubed if you go to a
假设f(a)等于a的三次方 如果你
calculus textbook and look up the table
翻看微积分课本上的导数公式表
of formulas you see that the slope of the
你会发现这个函数的斜率
function again the derivative of this
即这个函数的导数
function is equal to 3a squared so you
等于3乘以a的平方
can get this formula out of a calculus textbook
你可以从微积分课本上查到这个公式
so what this means so the way to
所以这是什么意思呢
interpret this is as follows let's take
同样地举一个例子
a equals 2 as an example again
我们再次令a等于2
so f of a or a cubed is equal to 8 does
所以a的三次方等于8
2 to power 3 so if we give a tiny little
即2的三次方 如果我们又将a增大一点点
nudge you find that f of a is about
你会发现f(a)的值
eight point zero one two and feel free
大约为8.012 你可以自己检查一遍
to check this take two point zero zero
如果我们取8.012
one two three you find that is very
你会发现2.001的三次方
close to eight point zero one two and
和8.012很接近
indeed when a is equal to 2 that's 3
事实上 当a等于2时
times 2 squared that's equal to 3 times
导数值为3乘以2的平方
4 is equal to 12 so the derivative
即3乘以4等于12 所以导数公式
formula predicts that if you now nudge a
表明如果你将a向右移动
to the right by a tiny little bit f of a
很小的一段距离
should go up 12 times as much and indeed
那么f(a)将会增大向右移动距离的12倍
this is true when a went up by point 001
所以当a增加0.001时
f of a went up 12 times as much by point 012
f(a)增大了四倍 即0.012
just one last example and then we'll
来看最后一个例子
wrap up let's say the f of a is equal to
假设f(a)是一个log函数
the log function right so I'm going to
即f(a)=log(a)
write log of a and I'm going to use a
写作log(a) 然后我将使用
umm base e logarithm so some people
一个以e为底数的对数函数 有些人
write that as ln of a so if you go to
可能会写作ln(a)
calculus textbooks you find that when
所以如果你去看微积分课本
you take the derivative of log of a and
那么log(a)的导数
so this is a function that just looks
注意函数log(a)的图像是这样的
like that the slope of this function is
函数log(a)的斜率
given by 1 over a so the way to
应该为a分之1 所以我们
interpret this is that if a is any value
可以解释如下 如果a取任何值
again let's just keep using equals 2 as
比如又取a等于2
an example um and you nudge a to the
然后又把a
right by 0.001 you would expect f of a
向右边移动0.001 那么f(a)将增大a分之1
to go up by 1 over a that is by the
即函数f(a)的导数
derivative times the amounts that you
乘以你增大a的值(0.001)
increase a so in fact um if you pull up a
事实上 如果你借助计算器的话
calculator you find that as a is equal
你会发现当a等于2时
to 2 f of a is about 0.69315 and if you
f(a)约为0.69315
increase f and if you increase a to 2
如果你增加f 如果你将a增大到2.001
point 001 then f of a is about 0.69365
那么f(a)约为0.69365
so it's gone up by 0.0005
所以f(a)增大了0.0005
indeed if you look at the formula for the
事实上 如果你查看导数公式
derivative when a is equal to 2 d/da f of
当a等于2的时候
a is equal to 1/2 so this derivative
导数值d/da f(a)等于二分之一
formula predicts that if you pump up a
所以导数公式表明 如果你
by 0.001 you will expect f of a to go up
把a增大0.001
by only one half as much and one half
f(a)将只会增大0.001的二分之一
0.0001 is 0.0005 which is exactly what we
即0.0005 这就是我们所得到的值
got right then when a goes up by 0.001
当a增大0.001时
going from a close to two equals two
从a等于2增大到非常近的2.001
point 001 f of a goes up by half as
f(a)增大了
much as this are going up by
这个(0.001)的二分之一
approximately 0.0005 so if you draw that
即增大了大约0.0005 所以如果你在这儿
little triangle if you will is that if
画个小三角形 你就会发现
on the horizontal axis goes up by 0.001
如果x轴增加了0.001
under vertical axis log of a goes up by
那么y轴上的函数log(a)
half of that so point 0005 and so that one
将增大0.001的一半 即0.0005
over a 1/2 in this case when a is equal
所以a分之1 当a等于2时这里是二分之一
to 2 that's just the slope of this line
这个二分之一就是当a等于2时
when a is equal to 2 so that's it for
这条线的斜率 这些就是有关
derivatives there's just two take-home
导数的一些知识 所以在这个视频中
messages from this video first is that
你只需要记住两点 第一点是
the derivative of the function just
函数的导数
means the slope of a function and the
就是函数的斜率
slope of a function can be different at
而函数的斜率
different points on the function in our
在不同的点是不同的
first example where f of a equals 3a
在第一个例子中f(a)=3a
this is a straight line the derivative was
这是一条直线 在任何点
the same everywhere it was 3 everywhere
它的斜率都是相同的 均为3
but for other functions like f of a
但是对于函数f(a)=a^2
equals a squared or f(a) equals log of a
或者f(a)=log(a)
the slope of the line varys so the
它们的斜率是变化的
slope or the derivative can be different
所以它们的导数或者斜率
at different points on the curve so does
在曲线上不同的点处是不同的
the first take away derivative just
所以这是第一个你需要记住的
means slope of a line second takeaway is
即导数就是斜率 第二点是
that if you want to look up the
如果你想知道
derivative of a function you can flip
一个函数的导数
open your calculus textbook or look at
你可参考你的微积分课本或者维基百科
Wikipedia and often get a formula for
然后你应该就能
the slope of these functions at
找到这些函数的导数公式
different points so that I hope you have
最后 我希望
an intuitive understanding of
你能通过我生动的讲解
derivatives or slopes of lines let's go
掌握这些有关导数和斜率的知识
into the next video we'll start to talk
接下来让我们进入下一个视频
about the computation graph and how to
下一课 我们将讲解计算图
use that to compute derivatives of more complex functions
以及如何用它来求更加复杂的函数的导数